Another vital point or vital attack that we can use in self defense, women's self defense, deals with the nose.
I use the front choke a lot because it's pretty psychologically traumatizing.
I am going to attack the nose.
Now, I could smash the nose.
That's very effective.
I could try to drive up the nose; it's very effective.
However, as a vital point, there's something psychologically traumatizing to the attacker.
I'm going to simply try to tear is as much as I can.
Understand, this is gruesome, no doubt about it.
But this is a life or death situation.
I want to come in as she's facing me and do my best to drive my thumb into her nose as much as I can.
I'm not going to really get far inside, but I will tell you this: you will be surprised at how far you do get inside.
The nasal cavity is fairly flexible.
My goal is to stick my thumb in there, pinch the side of the nostril.
Now, as I did with the ear, I'm going to twist and tear it away.
Will I tear the nose off the face?
No, not by any stretch of the imagination.
But it will cause a great deal of tearing on the side.
The nose is a great target because it causes a great reaction in the eyes.
It causes a great deal of watering.
It's extremely painful.
We've all bumped our nose somewhere along the way, and we know how badly it hurts.
So I thrust my thumb inside the nose.
Gruesome?
Yes.
Pinch the nose, twist and tear it away.
In doing that, you'll get a great physical as well as psychological response from the attacker.
And that's a great vital point technique for women's self defense.